Hello everybody.
We're happy to see you all at this
webinar. Uh and what we're going to talk
about uh while we just you know getting
started and warming up. Um let's wait
for everybody to join and briefly start
with the round of introductions. Um I'm
Mike CEO and founder at Costag. And
today with me is Back. Yeah. And I'm
Barack. I maintain React Native Builder
Bob and interested in brownfield in
general.
Nice. So today
um we're we're going to talk about
um brow right which is basically a way
to start using react native inside
existing mobile applications. Um and
I've been doing brownfield for a while.
Uh I think ever since we started uh the
company brownfield was obviously one of
the most important topics that people
were interested in. uh because you know
sometimes we start new applications but
many times we actually have to deal with
something that is already existing and
um yeah I spent quite some time on the
library side and react native side uh
you are on the application front end
side and I I know like the reason you're
here is because you actually tried all
all the things that I'm talking about
yourself so we can
exactly
yeah so
um that project you're working on right
now uh the project with the browfield
integration um
like okay we'll get to it probably uh
during the during the during the
presentation um I'm just trying to
figure out the screen sharing situation
here um I guess probably the best way
would be to do it this
way
Okay, hold on a
second. So, we'll start briefly and uh
to do so I will be sharing um the
slides. Back, do you have setup for
sharing the slides in the meantime? Uh
because I'm having some technical
difficulties. I wonder if
okay just a second and I can share
that'll be very helpful um so we can get
started u meanwhile I can briefly walk
you through the agenda for today uh the
agenda is that we'll do a short
presentation uh like overall we we will
spend up to an hour talking about
brownfield uh what we will start with
first is going through a bit of slides
where we can talk about uh react native
um how it array and and all the things
and then um we will talk about uh
implementation itself and how how all
these pieces sort of uh play uh
together. So um yeah we already went
through the introductions so uh we can
start with the react native architecture
um which is um the diagram we have on
the next slide and ah it's beautiful
with the animations. So um basically
before we go deeper into react native
brownfield let's talk about how react
native works under the hood so you can
have a perfect understanding of it and
then a lot of things that we will be
talking about will become much easier uh
for you to sort of understand. So React
Native has two layers. The first one,
JavaScript layer is where you write your
code, right? It's the UI components,
business logic. Uh it's all using
React's intuitive uh component model. So
this is you know clean a a very clean
way to write platform independent code
and describe what you want to do. And
then below that you have the native
layer and this is the magic that then
turns your React code into real platform
specific components and behaviors.
Now for example like on this slide when
you write your component to show a movie
card the native layer in the middle and
I see bur you don't have the fancy font
library that I have with that there's
supposed to be an arrow in the middle
but question mark is also okay because
like what is really going on here is the
is the is the fun part but um you know
that native layer is what makes the
component on the left side be an actual
native component on the right side and
the Key here is that you only write your
code once on the top on the top side. So
the native layer takes care of all the
complexity for you. And you know that
separation of concerns is what actually
makes React Native pretty powerful for
crossplatform
development. And then uh let's talk
about separation of concerns. React
Native provides the entire native
implementation for you. So green stuff
um it's not just you know native code
with few modules it's actually an entire
uh rendering engine uh tooling for
debugging profiling and access to native
APIs. So everything that you need to
write performant native code is there
for you. You can just focus on building
cool features with JavaScript.
So don't not having to worry about
native is is one great thing. Another is
faster time to market. And the reason
for that is first of all you're working
with JavaScript and TypeScript. So
languages that are very fast to develop
in right and then
uh they also have excellent LLM and AI
tool support. Um that accelerates your
development process from day one. And uh
if you could bur just press space twice,
we'll see the beautiful cards. Yes. And
then the third one is the uh when you
build a feature for React Native, you
can deploy it across multiple platforms
simultaneously, right? So you don't have
to build the same feature once um three
four times. You can just build it once.
So that is second benefit. Another
benefit is uh fewer bags across
platforms. So first of all when you find
and fix an issue that fix will apply
across all platforms immediately and
there is no need to fix the same issue
you know multiple times in different
code bases and then second of all even
better once you test things and and and
sort of fix it you can verify it once
and kind of make sure that it it is
working everywhere and that dramatically
reduces your overall Q&A time and
finally perhaps the most practical
advantage of all is the knowledge
transfer. So you know first of all you
have or you are a web developer so you
already know JavaScript. Second of all
we all as long as we are uh developers
understand the the development patterns
of the web and lastly we all know React.
So that means you know everybody who's
either writing JavaScript is more or
less familiar with web development or is
building with React can get productive
with React Native immediately. And that
is pretty awesome because once you start
integrating React Native into your
mobile apps, you're opening your native
code bases to a huge number of people
that wouldn't be able to to sort of work
with your codebase uh otherwise. That
makes scaling much easier. Now that we
understand all the benefits, let's talk
about the actual brownfield journey to
achieve the shared codebase. Before we
do that, let's try to visualize it. So
this is more or less the state you have
today.
web using React and typically Android
and iOS using Cotlin and Swift and each
platform has its own implementation, own
development cycle, own maintenance
needs. And then on the right side, this
is where we want to be. We want to have
unified React Native codebase powering
all
platforms. One implementation, one
deployment cycle, short maintenance.
So what we really want to do is we want
to get from this which is same component
written twice in both swift
android to this a very clean and elegant
React component that works across all
the
platforms. I know this looks pretty
sweet but in reality React Native never
replaces your entire codebase. it be,
you know, we often talk about React
Native migrations and people go crazy
with, you know, chasing this 100% React
Native rewrite. In practice, what really
ends up being is React Native being part
of your stack like in this case
coexisting with Swift, iOS, Cotlin um on
Android and Swift on iOS. So, what is
the advantage if if that's the case?
Well, one of them, my favorite one to be
honest, is that you can keep your apps
fully functional and continue
development while you work towards
sharing code with React
Native. You can gradually integrate
React Native features into your
application and the migration strategy
you choose and we'll talk about
migration strategies later. And then you
get to keep native cover makes sense. So
say you have some native functionalities
where you care about performance or you
typically deal with some sort of secure
sensitive data, you can keep that as is.
There is no need to rewrite everything
to React Native if it doesn't make
sense. And lastly, you can choose how
fast you want to do it. You can take
necessary measurements and decide what's
best for your users. That's pretty cool,
right?
So let's see how we can make that
migration happen. Uh so today we're
going to show you how to take one react
component and integrate it with existing
native applications. And we will have um
two strategies. The simple one and this
is sort of the simple one you can get
started with the one you can see online.
Um and we'll do it just for the sake of
setting up the context and then we will
talk about the more advanced way of
doing brownfield applications. the one
that you know Burak has been working on
in production that I've been uh working
on as well and and so you will be able
to see some actual production cases with
that and at the end if you have any
questions or you will want to follow up
later we will be able to accommodate
that as well and for the sake of doing
that demonstration we will be using iOS
for two reasons first of all we don't
have time to to do both and second of
all typically iOS is always easier uh to
present unless unless Unless we are
talking to somebody who's been talking
Java for the past 20 years, then it
might be the other way around. So, a lot
of what we'll be talking about, like I
said, is publicly available knowledge,
at least for the first part. Um, you can
check the official documentation of
React Native. Very good resource, highly
recommended. Uh, and the React team did
pretty good job making that
documentation a very good resource. So,
I would say it is worth giving them a
shout out on this occasion.
So the first thing we'll start with is
the project structure. The key is
organization. Uh you know you want your
React Native code to live alongside your
native application. This means creating
a directory for React Native somewhere
inside your actual native application
typically sidebyside iOS and Android
folders. That way you can keep things
organized. And again um this is just one
way to do it. You can do it any way you
want but typically if you were to follow
the React Native getting started guide
you would do this because that's just
the way uh it is recommended and is
actually very simple. Next we we need to
get React Native and depend and its
dependencies working and this is a very
important step. Now if you have
JavaScript background you're like okay
whatever that is basic knowledge the the
challenge is and this is the reason why
we have created the advanced uh way of
doing brownfield is this is not the case
for the rest of your team so the
challenge is and we'll talk about
challenges later once you integrate
react native now everybody on your team
has to run npm install and obviously if
you have a team of 50 native engineers
that is not optimal from many for many
reasons So we will have to install it
with npm. That means you must install
Node.js as well. Once that's once that's
done, uh you will get node modules
folder in your workspace typically uh
very close to typically very close to
where you install your React Native. Um
and this is where React Native will be
as well as other dependencies. And this
is the this is the React Native is
inside node modules. And the reason for
that is React Native does not use cocoa
pods or Maven for distributing its
binaries because a lot of there is a lot
of dependencies between JavaScript and
native. Uh their decision has been made
to sort of go back to shipping binaries
with npm package. Um so if you have
native background you might be slightly
confused but this is just to make sure
that we don't have some dependency
misaligned versioning issues later in
production when using JavaScript.
Now once we have that we can jump to
configuring pot file and again this is
iOS so on Android that would be gradal
um and um if you already have pot file
like many iOS projects do uh you will go
there and you will add react native line
you can see there in the middle and
that's where uh that's where that's
where things get get started. Um so
there is a lot of code here and on the
next slide I have highlighted the actual
code that is specific to React Native.
If you're starting fresh, React Native
provides a P file you can use out of the
box. Either way, the end result is the
same. You have this P file and that P
file will uh generate an entire XC
workspace when you run P install, which
is the next
step. After that, once you run it, you
will receive an XC
workspace on your uh inside your
project. um as you can see on the next
slide is going to be a um inside iOS
folder X Xcode project an XC workspace.
So the idea is that once this is created
you have everything set up and you can
start using the XC workspace. So if
you've been using if you've been
building a fresh native iOS application
you probably didn't have XC workspace.
So this will be a new project for you.
But in reality all the projects or most
of them are already using kaka pods and
are probably quite lo and old. And in in
such cases you will have xc workspace
already and adding react native will
feel a bit like adding another library
dependency to your project. It's just
that this one will be compiled kind of
from source. That's why you will feel
like you're struggling with JavaScript
even though it's a dependency of your
project.
So now before we render React Native
inside, let's take a look at the
index.js of React Native application.
This will help us understand what's
going on. And as you can see, there is
so much stuff inside that I had to do
the scroll animation. Um, and we're not
going to talk about everything here. Uh,
in fact, we're just going to focus on
what's most important, which is app
registry component that I highlighted uh
for you on the next slide. Um, the app
registry is a module that allows you to
explicitly register React components
that can be referenced from the native
side. And if you are new to React Native
Brownfield or adapting React Native,
this is probably the key highlight that
that you have to keep in mind and
understand. Um when you register react
component with
um reg ru app registry you can reference
it from the native side and the strategy
you choose is up to you. You can
register one typically that's what's by
the default which is just one big root
component but doesn't have to be right.
If you decide that you want to replace
five components gradually, so starting
starting small and going up the tree, in
that case you may decide to register
few. And as you can see on the next
slide, uh we have uh RCT root view
factory which is an abstraction provided
by React Native on iOS. And we can use
that helper to instantiate a UI view
that will be pointing to that React
component. And that is the module name
and initial properties in case you
wanted to pass some additional options
and we'll talk about it later as well uh
in Burak part how we can leverage that
to provide some additional abstraction
for type safety specifically. So when we
put that view on the screen uh that that
root view UI view what will happen is on
the next slide you will see we have a
hello world the purple component this is
the full screen react component. So as
you can see it is really just taking um
um sorry in this case let's let's I
actually made a mistake so let me um go
back one sentence this is the default
react application actually so what I was
supposed to say is that the purple one
is actually react component so when you
start a fresh react application uh the
app registry will instantiate this uh
hello world and the purple stuff will be
hello world now on the next slide and
this is uh what I was meaning to say is
when you register multiple components in
this case active order bottom tabs and
hello world you'll see that you have an
opportunity to render three of them on
the native side and in this case we're
rendering them one next to another which
obviously uh makes sense but you know
imagine you were building an Uber and
one of the components was the header
another one was I don't know the Uber
rides component and the last one was
payments module so It's sort of a lot of
flexibility in here depending on how you
want to do it and this is the strength
of React Native the fact that it
seamlessly integrates with your existing
code bases and at the same time it
provides the primitives it uses native
primitives as well. So it is at the end
of the day UI view. No way you can
differentiate it if you've done your
styling right. And that's it. If you end
up following this route, you should
follow the documentation step by step.
The next slide will show you the link.
This is the link to um Xcode additional
Xcode steps. And you know for the
bravity of this uh webinar, I decided to
skip some steps. So, I hope that we made
this easy part even easier and it seems
like super super fun stuff to do. I have
to give you a little warning that there
are a few more steps in there that you
should actually pay attention to and I
guess um that brings us to the
challenges. So, let me just do a quick
introduction to Burak's part by saying
what's wrong with this approach and that
will set the scene for the second part.
Um, one significant consideration is
that your native development team will
need to work with the JavaScript
pipeline. Right? Like I said, this isn't
necessarily a blocker, but it can create
friction when even small React Native
features require all engineers to handle
additional uh workflow steps. And from
my personal experience and I've been you
know uh working with React Native for
it's crazy to say but I believe it's
been it's going to be around 9 years h
this is all this has always been an
issue um you know what is my native
native steam reaction going to be and so
on and so on and second of all um good
understanding of JavaScript ecosystem.
So without good understanding of the
JavaScript ecosystem, troubleshooting
these issues will be a challenge because
okay like I'm working with JavaScript
daytoday and now with AI and cursor it
is even easier but every time you know
just just just think about like if
you're a JavaScript engineer just think
about how many times you had an issue
with native build problems and you spent
hours troubleshooting that learning how
cmake works and stuff like that. It is
the same for native developers just the
other way around. So depending on your
background, you may uh you may realize
quickly and early on that putting that
into your codebase, the stakeholders in
your team will quickly say this is a
no-go because we're not adding
additional technical debt. We are
supposed to move faster not slow
everybody down. So these are the
challenges and from those challenges uh
we came up with the idea for advanced
the reactive integration and this is
what Burak has been working with. So
that said I'll I'll pass it over to you
Back now and um I'm also happy to help
with the slides but if you have your
setup up and running feel free to
continue. Sure I can go on. Okay. So
again, um, we have lots of these
challenges and I think like these
challenges personally hurt me because
like I can imagine a native team lead
stepping in and telling me what to add
or what to not add to my React Native
application and like that wouldn't be
the most ideal case. So to solve all
these problems um, we have developed a
more advanced React Native integration.
Um, we use a component that we call the
bridge component. So let's take a look
at what the bridge component looks like
and what it exactly
does. Okay, at a high level, this is
what our advanced React Native
integrations architecture is. Um, we
have three main layers, three main
boxes. We got the React Native layer at
the top. So the React Native layer
contains our JavaScript code, the React
code and then we have a bridge component
just below React Native layer uh which
sits just in the middle and this
component is tested handling all the
communication between my JavaScript code
iOS and Android. So when I have to call
the native API, I have to make a call to
um my native application. I want to show
something like show a model that's
implemented in my native Android
application. What I do from JavaScript
is make a call to the bridge component
and then the bridge component is tasked
with um going to the Android app or the
iOS app and calling the right APIs and
then showing me the model that I wanted
to show. So the bridge component is
tasked with communication. Um it just
glues everything together. It glues my
JavaScript code with everything else.
And let's talk about the benefits and um
some of the key challenges. So first of
all um this approach provides some clean
packaging. Um when I have my React
Native application um package this means
I ship everything as a pre-ompiled
artifact. What this means is I build my
React Native code in advance before I'm
passing it to the native teams. Um, and
this will mean for them that they won't
have to pay the price of building React
Native if they want to use it in the
app. You build it. You pay the price of
building React Native. You as a React
Native team pay it and then once native
team receives that package, they don't
have to pay it anymore because um the
code has already been built. They just
have to consume a library. Um and then
we have a single package and then in
that package we have all our React
Native components with their business
logic register. So this means we I have
a single package with everything about
React Native. I don't have to worry
about anything else. Um, and then I
assume you have some native engineers
that already know how to consume a
library like how to consume a library
from Maven, how to consume an XC
framework or even as an SPM package. Um,
we have this approach so the native
developers can just take the React
Native code and add it as a any library
to the native
applications. Um, and then let's look at
how it looks like in practice. So what
we do is we create an Xcode project an
Xcode library and that library produces
an XC framework file on iOS and we have
a pod file in the example but that
doesn't mean that you have to add coca
pods to your native application. It just
gives you an XC framework which means
you can either directly consume it um
use coca pods to consume it or you can
also use SPM's ability to ship XC
frameworks. So if you have a like pure
swift codebase that you don't want to
add any coal pods, you don't want to add
um any XC frameworks manually because
you might be um interested in not having
to deal with the versions, you can just
use SPM and the SPM can handle grabbing
the right XC framework for you. And then
on Android, we have um an AAR file. So
you can push this to Maven, your private
one, and then you can just consume it as
any other library. Here we have the
implementation um and this just consumes
our react native
application. Um so let's take a look at
um what like what am I sending now? So I
I said that we have a package but that
package what like what's inside that
package inside that package is we have a
library and all the libraries need to
have a public interface because when the
native developers import that library
into their apps they have to somehow be
able to call some code like load a viv
um lo a viv controller to like sh react
native application. So what we do is we
design a carefully crafted public API
interface. Um so we typically we
typically expose a VF controller like in
this but uh we can also pick to just
ship a VF. You don't have to always like
ship a V controller. Um in this case
what we do is we call the React root
view factory API to create a root view
and then this all happens internally. So
your application devs don't have to know
what the react would be factory does.
It's just our um internal
interface. So once that's all done
um yeah so once all that that's all done
we go to the native application and just
import the library that we published
earlier. In this case you can take a
look at the importer library line and
once library is imported we load our viv
controller as any other. um it says let
react vc um equals to our hello world
view controller and this is the view
control that we have um exposed from our
library and then once that's done we can
obviously present it do anything we want
and that's just react native at this
point you don't have to worry about
anything else
um the second benefit is we can enable
type safety this way because normally
when you have the um classic approach or
like the simpler approach you you really
don't have a public interface. You just
have the react internals. You can use
them and you basically call any view
with a string name and that doesn't seem
safe because uh what I can do is instead
of hello world I can do hello world uh
just forgot the d and my view is not
going to be loading. But in this case um
we can have type safety in our public
interface and that will ensure that the
native developers don't import the um
like import with a wrong
name. Um so we have strong type
checking. We can also pass the arguments
with correct types to the library. And
then lastly, thanks to the compile time
safety, I don't even have to run my app
to see if React Native is working
properly because I have uh static type
checking and everything is if like
everything has the correct types,
everything should work
properly. Um and then here we have an
example of what the type safety looks
like. Um so in this case I am creating a
new strct called hello world config and
this internally accepts um a show user
greeting boolean and then once we have
that what we can do is we can go back to
our view controller class and accept
this config structure as the init
parameter. So when you want to create a
new hello world view controller, you
also have to pass this config and what
we do internally after that is um there
is this argument that the create root
view function accepts called initial
properties. So whatever you pass to the
initial properties are going to be
passed to the react native uh the react
components props. And what this means is
when I render my component, my show user
grading prop will be whatever the native
engineer sets it
to. Um, and then here we have the React
code. For instance, I have my
application. This const app is my React
functional component that it receives my
props as arguments. And inside that
props, I have my show user greeting
constant. And then based on that, I can
either show the hello world or not. And
I receive this prop from the native
site. I don't have this defined anywhere
in my react
application. Um and then in the native
side what I do is um when I am consuming
uh the hello world view of controller
from my application I first create my
config and creating that I have my hello
world config and then I just pass it um
the props that I want. In this case I
have true as show user greeting and then
I just pass it to my hello world view
controller. And notice that this is all
type safe. So if I ever try to pass
something to my React component that
doesn't even exist, um it's not going to
be a problem because I have everything
strictly type. I have compile time type
type safety.
Um and then also it's um it would be
nice to mention that oh I have my react
native views and I have my native
application and what I can do is I can
take
my native views and then uh take my
react native views and then put it into
the native application but it's also
important to say that I can do the exact
opposite. I can get my native views like
let's say I have built a custom payroll
screen that I want to show but inside my
react native portion what I can do is I
can wrap it and then just push to the
react native um and once that's done my
native application will render my n
react native component and then the
react native component will render the
native component and actually this is
what happens with react native when you
render text when you render any views
it's going to be showing the um the
native component itself when you use a
web view for instance, it's going to use
a native web view. So why shouldn't it
be possible to do it with any other
views?
Um yeah, so I think Mike you can take it
over now. Okay, thank you Burak. So that
was the um advanced way of doing things.
So now you more or less know how to
approach those two things. Um so let's
talk about the universal best practices.
So the things that make sense regardless
of which one approach you go with and
actually even regardless of whether you
even choose React Native in the first
place. So this might be interesting for
you regardless. So let's talk about
migration strategy. The first one most
companies can't really pose development
or migrate everything at once. So first
of all we typically recommend an
iteration screen by screen approach. So
this is the first step. Then the idea is
to start small, validate React Native in
a control environment and finally
gradually expand based on the success.
So let's have a look at uh the
application structure. Um this is a
typical structure may depend on you know
your application but you know typically
you would have login dashboard maybe
some screens FAQ and help. So we we have
to look uh for the best candidate for
the migration and um on the highlighted
slide uh on the section like on this
slide now you can see I highlighted uh
FAQ and help which are usually the best
starting points. They're often
non-critical even though you want your
users to get some help. Um you typically
already use a web view there. Uh so you
know that makes them perfect fit for
native because you likely have some
JavaScript under the hood anyway. uh and
we can take application approach but
also um the next um alternative approach
is a component level migration and in
this case we can be even more granular.
We can instead of replacing the whole
FAQ screen we can take advantage of um
uh what Burex um has been showing us at
the very end with the sort of
birectional approach. We can go even
lower and register instead of a big FAQ
screen. Imagine you created five
different small React components or even
if you have React on the web, you would
have a component for everything because
everything is a component. So you could
have a button or you could have a
navbar. All these can be ported over to
React Native component by component. So
you don't have to go for the whole
screen if you're concerned that you want
to start even smaller. So in this case
FAQ item would be the smallest one and
then we will be going up building up
this as we continue. So that is the sort
of migration approach. Now when we
migration another best practice is the
sort of brownfield uh setup in general.
Um we shouldn't aim for
100% React Native because brownfield is
a valid end goal. it's not a temporary
state. Um so if we go over to the next
section uh we will see I created a
breakdown um of you know how you can
think about using native code where it
makes sense. Uh so first of all you know
keep in mind that React Native Excel is
coexisting with your native codebase and
this is uh this should be viewed as a
first class solution not a compromise
and and some features like CPU intensive
work or crossplatform C++ libraries make
more sense to keep native like there is
no need to rewrite these in JavaScript.
In fact if you've been following trends
the trend is the opposite actually. On
the other hand, your UI or business
logic uh makes perfect sense to be
written in React Native because you can
share it with your web implementation.
And finally, another universal best
practice that you will need is very
crucial is the monitoring. Um so you
have to implement proper telemetry to
understand your results in production.
First of all, uh one good practice that
we use of code stack is um DMAG
methodology which is define, measure,
analyze, improve, control. It is a very
nice and lightweight framework to how on
how to think about finding performance
problems, analyzing them and fixing them
in your codebase, making sure they never
happen again. Second of all, there is
real user monitoring for production
insights, which means getting actual
data from user devices and seeing how
how the results of your work translate
to actual end users. And finally, you
can consider using open telemetry for
for comprehensive data collection. And a
little sneak peek, we've been using this
internally for our customers. There is a
library coming up. So if you're rolling
out your custom solution right now or
you feel like ah I would have to sort of
build it myself there will be something
from us for you to use. So getting all
that all together
um here is an example of hypothetical
migration from a web view uh and how we
can measure it to provide us feedback.
Thanks to real user monitoring, we can
have a very good information before and
after uh how the change or introduction
of React Native is impacting the
performance of a particular screen. In
this case, everything you see on the
screen is made up, but it's just here to
show you the sort of reason behind doing
all that. And if if we started using
React Native say for um help section or
FAQ section, what we typically see with
our customers is much better performance
of sections that were web views
otherwise. Uh much better satisfaction
because the native layouts and UI
provides much better user experience and
after all overall the impact is
positive. You can see faster loading
time. Everybody is happy. We are we have
validated the approach and we are ready
to go. So as you can see this is all
very good and you you might be asking
yourself question like who's really
doing that and let me tell you that
everybody's doing this pretty much
everybody unless you're a startup but
typically these two players are worth a
shot. Uh Shopify recently completed the
migration from fully native to React
Native. So they transitioned and
repurposed their entire their entire
organization from being native
organization to react and react native
organization. They still do maintain
native pieces where it makes sense but
but in principle they are react native
first right now and they're they're
pretty interesting company to sort of
call out because typically and this is
what we presented to you today as well
the migration strategies to start from
bottom up take least important screens
validate how reit behaves if you're
satisfied keep going further Shopify
they have a lot of great resources
online. They did total opposite and we
did podcast with them together. Uh you
should uh check it out React Universe uh
on air podcast with Shopify Mustafa Ali
who's the sort of technical person
behind that effort. And so we talk a lot
about challenges of migrating to React
Native including you know what happens
with your native engineers but typically
uh what I wanted to sort of call out
here is the the fact that they started
from the top. Their approach was let's
order screens by impact and start
rewriting the biggest screens and most
important screens first. Reason for that
very simple if the technology is not
going to satisfy our requirements we'd
rather get to know that very early
rather than at the end. And so it worked
out for them as well. Something to keep
in mind as an anecdote I guess uh
because their engineering resources are
pretty pretty heavy. And then we have
meta obviously who created react native
and they were using react native in
brownfield from the very beginning. In
fact this is the way they do it all the
way commitment you can keep uh you can
you can be safe that that use case will
always be uh important. They use it in
marketplace which is serving billions of
people every day huge number performing
very well and marketplace is from what
I've been reading online the reason why
people got excited about Facebook again
especially the younger audience uh
because people are making deals on
marketplace which you know um is is what
what is attracting meta users to
Facebook application again which in
result only shows how important that
technology for meta is the trend is
clear companies are increasingly
adopting React Native and you know
latest uh news and research from uh the
US shows that most startups are
recruiting React Native developers first
for the speed of use time to market and
you also have to keep in mind that with
the sort of increase of AI in our
everyday's lives and increase of you
know agents for development react and
react native
point because LMS are pretty good at
writing that code. So if that sounds
like a plan, uh before we jump into Q&A,
I wanted to um highlight two things. Uh
the first one is um this is very easy to
do. I mean at least to get started if
you have a native application and you
feel like you're not moving as fast as
you could or you're exploring React
Native or you maybe started but you
didn't completed it. Whatever is your
status, you can get a production ready
solution under a month based on our
experience. We're happy to help you with
this, but if you have your own
engineers, we're also happy to provide
you some feedback, tips, and tricks.
Point is you can start you can join the
React Native community within a month
from today if you decide. And um and and
so I guess at this point we can uh park
it up. Just one more slide where uh ah
it didn't update. I updated in the
meantime, but it's okay. Scan this QR
code to join our newsletter, but also um
I'm going to type it in the chat as
well. Um but I'm also going to say it.
Feel free to email me uh at
mikecolstack.com and we're more than
happy um to answer any of the follow-up
questions you have if you either don't
want to talk about your application on a
webinar um because maybe it's under NDA
or something that you're not feeling
like you want to share. This one uh we
can take offline and we can talk about
it. So, we have roughly 10 to 15 minutes
left for some Q&A. And I guess um if you
want to participate in the Q&A, feel
free to drop a question in the chat. In
the meantime, I can uh kick it off with
my first question. My first question
would be uh to you, Borak, given the
advanced setup.
Um how like how did you like how was the
performance and reception after you
started that migration? We talked about
theory. What about the actual uh
feedback from uh from the client?
Okay. So what we have done is we
implemented the first stage which was
the PC stage and the client already had
a react native application and they
wanted to bring the react native only
features that they filled with web views
to their native app. So again, as you
said, they wanted to replace their web
views and I can say this that um I can
say this happily that they were pretty
happy with replacing uh some of their
web views like their payment. All of
those were changed and they had better
UX thanks to React Native having a
better UX than web views. That is
interesting. So typically we've been
talking about you know you have native
app and you want to move faster and
maybe start migrating but uh you can
see you can see from uh from their case
like you may have some other application
already and you may be like yeah why
don't we just uh use that instead. So um
we have two questions in the chat and
there are two related to each other. So
we'll start with the first one from
Alfredo. Thank you for the question. Is
there a GitHub repo with demo advanced
setup scaffolding? And another one which
is also related. Thank you for the
question. Is there any chance that this
framework for brownfield integration
will become open
source? Um I will let you bak answer
this one as well because you are sort of
more involved in that project than me.
So I'll let you take the um you know the
the glory um and answer that.
So people just ask us. So in general
people ask us when it's going to be open
sourced. Um so it's going to be an
easier question to answer. Is there any
chance 100% we're going to be open
sourcing the React Native framework that
we've been working on? Um soon let's
say. And if we have a GitHub repo with
the demo first of all we have a pending
PR in this framework that we have that
has this advanced workflow demo. And
then I think we also have another GitHub
repo that I'm not sure if we have open
it yet. Yeah. Uh so I can I can help
with that. So there there is a few
projects uh that we are working on right
now in this space. Um and I think the
best will be for me to try sharing my
screen and then I can walk you through
uh what we have here. So um let's see.
All right. So this is uh the first repo
uh the react native brownfield and um
react native brownfield is how it all
started many years ago. At first react
native brownfield was just a collection
of utilities uh for for doing different
migration for doing different
communication between react re native
and native. So all the RST review
factories that you've seen today on our
slides the sort of how do we migrate how
do we call UI view from native side and
that renders react native component that
is easy but then you have communication
issues how do I pass my data how do I
communicate react native navigation with
the native navigation when I dismiss
model and like it's two separate worlds
you have to connect with with with
themselves and this library is the
library that we created for Dart
purpose. It has six years already. So,
as you can see, it's been around for a
while. We are working on a complete
overhaul and bring in more features so
that all the benefits that you've seen
today with the automatic packaging will
be available in this library in the next
month. If you're interested in uh being
notified when it's ready, um our
newsletter is is good way to stay up to
date, but also just like I said, you can
email me at mike mike@colstack.com and
I'll be happy to follow up with you on
this one as well. And then uh we have
another one which as as far as I'm aware
we hadn't open sourced yet but I will
show you the landing page because we
have launched a waiting list um just
about uh just about last week. So um
this is it. It's called a React Native
framework. um you know metal last year
created I'm I'm not sure if like what's
the demographics here and how much
you're familiar with the react native
and framework situation there but let me
just fast track it fast forwarded and
say that we have
created and it's sort of being rolled
out as we speak to our customers we are
testing this in production because we
want to release it and make sure it's
awesome. This is our sort of collection
of utilities for building React Native
apps at a scale. Typically, if you were
researching React Native today, you've
came across Expo, and Expo is amazing,
but it is even better if you're building
from scratch. We see a lot of our
customers struggle with existing apps.
They struggle with their own CI/CD
pipelines and so many different ifs and
elsees about their infrastructure that
is just hard to satisfy at all. And so
we created this uh framework. On the
video here you see just a demonstration
of our build pipeline which means once
one of your engineers builds the app,
all of you get it for free
automatically. So there is no need to
rebuild it five times. just build it
once and everybody can run it which is
pretty cool. It's kind of like expo but
on your infrastructure and now for this
one we are working on a bunch of cool
new features and one of the features as
you can see we already have it because
we are already testing it is the
brownfield integration and brownfield
integration or the pull request that
Burak's been talking about is that
feature. So starting from the next month
when we do a public beta if you are
interested to join and participate in
that private beta email me
michaelsteam.com or go to the
enterprise-framework.colasttime.com to
read more about this and you will have
access to that. Basically what it is at
the end of the day is a common line
tool. So the idea is that you will be
able to just write an enterprise
framework build uh build um you know uh
build uh the the artifacts and then it
will depending on your choice either put
it on your internal repo or maybe send
it automatically to your native devs.
The idea will be that all these steps
are tricky. We're just making that super
easy so you can get started without
having to sort of figure that all out
yourself. Um so that would be uh that
would be the sort of ultimate ultimate
thing. You can sign up to the waiting
list. Uh we just released it last week.
We we got a bunch of people waiting uh
and it's pretty cool. So that is that is
a bunch of bunch of utilities that will
be helpful and you know you might be
thinking that this is not super u I
don't know like people often overlook
that piece and many times I see
companies dropping react native and they
often complain about react native itself
but in fact it's their the way they
integrated it that's the problem not the
framework itself. So it's a skill issue.
Yeah exactly.
Um exactly. So um that is the that is
regard itself. Now
um I wanted to follow up with the
question about the brownfield
integration you when you were building
the sort of PC and integrating that
since the client already had React
Native like how was the how was the sort
of native engineers versus React Native
situation there when you introduced
React Native to the main native app
everybody was sort of expecting that
because they were used to the pipeline
or like how did that So,
so how the app ended up being you know
from the CI/CD perspective and build
types as well. Yeah. So, um first of all
they had lots of native engineers and um
I think like their point initially was
not to replace the native apps with
React Native but just to bring new
features even faster. But they also told
us that the trend now in the company is
to fully migrate React Native
eventually. Um, and what we've done is
we had a React Native repository with
this brownfield code that we talked
about. They also had a shell application
that they could test React Native code
against and we had a CI pipeline that
packaged everything and published it via
the SPM and their private Maven
repository. And once that's done, you
can obviously go to your native
application and then on CI or where you
update your react native application or
even native application or even manually
you can just grab the latest swift
package manager package or the u the
gradal package.
Nice. So they had a pretty smooth
integration. That's pretty cool. And
then uh did you integrate just one
screen or like how granular was the
migration? What did you start?
Yeah. So we had two cases. Case A, we
had full screens and they were working
just fine. We could get any React Native
screen working in the native application
in the stack obviously. And then we had
the sec uh case B which was components.
So we take any component that's not full
screen and put it into native screen and
that case was also working brilliantly.
Nice. Nice. That's pretty cool. I
remember one of the first brownfield
scenarios that was often overlooked uh
but I was a huge fan of that was the
sort of um the um you know the the
birectional stuff. It's not that easy
but you know many times um typically
people are concerned about UI how we
make it feel unified and I just feel
like from my perspective like React
Native compared to flatter for example
like huge win is the sort of easy ease
of integration I I mean it's not like
flatter wouldn't be as easy I guess
probably right yeah I think so that is
would be easier to start from scratch
with flutter than to go with the
brownfield scenario which is which means
it's not flexible enough in this case.
Yeah, totally. Totally. And yeah, I
think you know um when we when we see a
lot of a lot of interesting
opportunities uh when it comes to using
React Native itself is is is typically
when like good opportunity is when you
have legacy code on the native side and
you just want to move faster maybe bring
your web features to it and sort of keep
the release train unified. But at the
same time um another good use case the
use case that we see every once in a
while is when there is a new platform
maybe or new device and you know if you
have three native code bases and now you
have to create a fourth one it's a
totally different discussion rather than
you're going to get it for free right
yeah I think we had the vision support
in few weeks or so
so it was crazy yeah yeah there you go I
mean I don't think it would
otherwise. Um, and you know, the great
thing about React Native in that case as
well, thanks to Oscar great work, is
that it hides away a lot of VR
primitives in a way that it's a
component. you're used to components and
and typically my challenge when it comes
to building VR apps or or AR apps to
that to that point is is the whole
different mental model and I'm just
struggling to learn that on top of the
native language and in this case it's
just kind of makes you feel like you're
at
home. Yeah, exactly. So I think like not
even VR but even with Android and iOS
you don't have to learn a bunch of
things to be able to build a native app.
like I don't I did I didn't know what a
fragment is until like last year and I
filled lots of mobile apps with React
Native. Yeah, you you're totally right.
I um my story with React Native started
when I built an iOS application for my
client and then they wanted me to build
Android because I was a fullstack guy.
They were like yeah just just do it
whatever and started learning Android
but then then I quickly realized there
is no way I'm ever mastering that. like
I just I just couldn't get around Java
and XML and all those activities. Just
the mental model of Android was totally
different from what I would you know
kind of expect. So you know even today
when I go through Android code I'm
somewhat surprised it is working. But
you know the point is thanks to reactive
I was able to just sort of roll with it
and that is also pretty cool because if
you start using it all the different
teams can be just one which is also
pretty cool I guess. Yeah. Yeah. Um
cool. So we have uh one last question on
the chat I think before we draw up which
is um like what are the best resources
for mastering um you know React Native.
Guess this is good question from for
many for many for many reasons. One of
them the fact that you know it's always
good to be great engineer but also you
know having the proper transition of
knowledge is also very important in your
organization as well. So I guess we can
you know while we wrap it up each one of
us can say what what do we think is the
best resource. I can say from my
perspective I find a lot of uh
satisfaction in just building stuff. So
um I was not really up to speed with
Swift and C++ as of last year but I
started building with natural modules
some native modules and then I was
somewhat forced to do it to learn it and
then I got up to speed very quickly. So
you know on top of obvious reasons and
obvious resources I would say nothing
beats actual coding is very satisfactory
especially if you're a designer. That
would be my my my my five cents. Yeah,
100% agree. And like when it comes to
resources, I guess a uh the official
documentation obviously and then b if
you have advanced scenarios, you have to
go and read the source code to some
degree. Yes, exactly. And um yeah, you
know, this reminds me of the live live
stream we did the other day when we were
going through the Vim uh tutorial. And
it's it's just like with anything, you
know, like just have to keep doing it
and then you will perfect it. Uh but if
you stop then then you won't. Um great.
So we you know, we did over an almost an
hour of of talking. I think it was fun.
You know, for me that was my first
webinar I think ever because for some
very strange reason I've never done it
before and it's super awesome because we
can practice the slides before
conference or after the conference and
you know share knowledge with you and a
smaller audience than live stream. So I
would say it was very fun and um I don't
know Burak for you I think it was also
one of the first times at CO. So yeah,
how was it? I enjoyed it. I enjoy
talking to you and so I actually like
love talking about this stuff in
general.
Yeah, I I do agree. I mean, every time
we're on the live stream or doing this,
I'm like not, you know, some people are
afraid or maybe freak out or have some,
you know, like stressed out and like
some people just genuinely just kind of
go with the flow and I see that's the
case, which is pretty awesome. Um,
awesome. So that wraps it up from my
side. I really wanted to thank everybody
for joining um and for staying over. We
did have a rather casual but steady
audience throughout the whole time which
is great. Means that nobody decided to
drop uh after seeing our beautiful
slides. Um so you can reach out to me
and Burak on Twitter. You can find us on
our website and email us as well. We
we're happy to talk with you and see you
next time I guess. Yep. See you next
time.